<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Obsidian Vault]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib\media\favicon.png</url><title>Obsidian Vault</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 06:44:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib\rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 06:44:23 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/index.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 06:13:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Active Directory?]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="post-thumbnail" src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/65c4efa1-7472-4aa0-aa8c-994385b67a25/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/cf0ba30b-ac69-496e-9b51-a58076dd2d7e/image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Active Directory centralizes the management of common components of a computer network in a single repository called Active Directory (AD). To explain it more simply, you can think of it as a database that stores information about company employees' account information (ID, password), computer information, and policies you want to enforce (ex: password is 9 or more characters long). I'm familiar with it because I manage a company server, but it can be a bit confusing when you first hear it. The server running this Active Directory is called a domain controller (DC).<br>
Advantages
<br>Centralized identity management: Easily control and control all users on your network.<br>
Security policy management: Configure security policies directly in Active Directory and apply them to users and computers across the network as needed.<br>There is convenience in being able to impose policies on the network and terminals within the network at will. It is very cumbersome to change settings on each computer, so this method is very convenient.<br>
Configuration
<br>At the heart of every Windows domain is Active Directory Domain Services (AD DS). This service acts as a catalog that holds information about all "objects" that exist on the network. Objects include users, groups, printers, shares, etc.<br><br>Users can be represented by two types of objects:<br>
<br>Person: A user generally refers to a person within an organization who accesses the network, such as an employee (company employee).
<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/2240c28c-4725-46d9-8986-841d0e3ff4e0/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>
<br>Services: You can define services to use for services such as IIS or MSSQL. In this case, the user only has the permissions necessary to run the specific service.
<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f500239b-d2d2-4785-91d3-b1bd96611d4e/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/8a395244-72fd-4e25-8412-99aee61a8b83/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><br>A machine is for any computer that joins an AD domain. Machines are considered security principals and are assigned accounts just like regular users. This account has limited permissions within the domain.<br>The computer account itself is a local administrator on the computer to which it is assigned and is usually accessible to anyone other than the computer itself, but can be logged in with a password.<br>Caution!: Your computer account password is automatically rotated and usually consists of 120 random characters.<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/09210179-107a-46f6-b6ef-0ba922829fc4/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><br>It is literally a user group. You can easily manage users by adding them to groups. The user automatically inherits all privileges attached to the group. Security groups are also considered security principals and therefore have permissions to network resources.<br>
You can sleep.<br>Caution!) A group can have both users and computers as members. Other groups may also be included if necessary.<br>Below is an example of a group.<br>Domain Group Description<br><br>Domain Administrator:&nbsp;Users in this group have administrative rights to the entire domain. By default, they can manage all computers in the domain, including DCs.<br>Server Administrator:&nbsp;Users in this group can administer domain controllers. Management group membership cannot be changed.<br>Backup Operator:&nbsp;Users in this group can access all files, ignoring permissions. Used to perform data backups on your computer.<br>Account Administrator:&nbsp;Users in this group can create or modify other accounts in the domain.<br>Domain Users:&nbsp;Includes all existing user accounts in the domain.<br>Domain Computers:&nbsp;Includes all existing computers in the domain.<br>Domain Controller:&nbsp;Includes all existing DCs in the domain.<br><br>A container object that allows you to categorize users and systems. It is primarily used to define sets of users with similar policy requirements. For example, employees in the sales department are likely to have a different set of policies in place than employees in the development department. And remember that a user can only belong to one OU at a time.<br>Automatically created organizational units<br><br>Embedded:&nbsp;Contains default groups that can be used on any Windows host.<br>Computer:&nbsp;All computers connected to the network are placed here by default. You can move it if necessary.<br>Domain Controller:&nbsp;The default OU that contains the DCs in the network.<br>User:&nbsp;Default users and groups that apply to the domain-wide context.<br>Managed Service Account:&nbsp;Holds the account used by services in the Windows domain.<br>Added) Different policies can be deployed individually for each OU via Group Policy Objects (GPOs). GPOs can contain policies targeting users or computers, allowing you to set criteria for specific computers and identities.<br>
<br>Difference between security group and organizational unit
<br>Organizational unit:&nbsp;Mainly used to apply policies<br>
Security Group:&nbsp;Used to grant permissions to resources<br><br>This part is similar for both users and machines. The idea is to separate devices and users based on their purpose. Just as it is good to separate intranet computers, development team personal computers, etc. from each other.<br><br>If you use Windows Domian, all credentials are stored on the domain controller. The user uses these credentials to authenticate to the service, and the service asks the domain controller to confirm the authentication is correct.<br>
Two protocols can be used for authentication: These are protocols that I occasionally encountered while studying hacking.<br>Kerberos: Used in newer versions of Windows. This is the default protocol for recent domains.<br>NetNTLM: A legacy authentication protocol maintained for compatibility.<br>Although I've heard that NetNTLM is often deprecated, both protocols live on most networks.<br><br>As your company grows, your network also grows. It's a natural result. As the number of services increases and the information to be managed increases, the size of the network also increases. We know how it grows. Whether it's an algorithm or a flow chart, it's a structure you'll definitely see.<br>you're right. It is a tree structure.<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/26ad27f9-1911-450e-be22-017ff2279379/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Active Directory supports multiple domain integration, allowing you to partition your network into independently manageable units. By making them share the same namespace, you can combine the domains in a tree form.<br>If your domain is split into two subdomains for UK and US branches, you can build a tree with a root domain and two subdomains called thm.local and thm.local, each with their own AD, computers, and users.<br>This partitioned structure gives you more control over who can access what in your domain. UK IT staff will have their own DC that manages only UK resources. For example, UK users cannot manage US users. In this way, the domain administrator at each branch has full control of its DCs, but not the DCs of other branch offices. You can also configure policies independently for each domain in the tree.<br>However, it is also common for companies with different namespaces to merge. What should I do in times like this? you're right. Just as the two Chinese characters for tree and neck come together to form the Chinese character for bush and forest,<br>the domain can also be a forest. Integrating multiple trees with different namespaces into the same network is called a forest.<br>By organizing multiple domains into trees and forests, you can have a nicely compartmentalized network in terms of management and resources. However, at some point, THM UK's users may need to access shared files on one of MHT ASIA's servers. To achieve this, domains arranged in<br>trees and forests are joined by trust relationships.<br>Simply put, a trust relationship between domains allows you to grant users from another domain access to resources in another domain. This relationship can be unidirectional or bidirectional.<br>This is how I looked into Active Directory. Normally, when managing a server, I only knew the concepts and moved on, but when I reflected on my knowledge properly, my perspective opened up more broadly. I need to gain more security and network knowledge in the future.]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\cs\서버-관리\eng\active-directory(eng).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/CS/서버 관리/Eng/Active Directory(Eng).md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:47:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/65c4efa1-7472-4aa0-aa8c-994385b67a25/image.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/65c4efa1-7472-4aa0-aa8c-994385b67a25/image.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ubuntu Docker Capacity Management(Eng)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f03cd953-edc3-4ae4-8b00-60576cf465e8/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>We encountered a difficult error while using Docker at work. The 4TB allocated to Ubuntu was insufficient, so the existing service was down. At first, we thought we could deal with it by deleting files or logs that were taking up a lot of space, but that wasn't the fundamental problem.<br>Since I spent a lot of time on this issue, I decided to share my solution for developers like me, especially those who develop and maintain Docker servers like me.<br><br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/72458452-fa5d-43e7-8f4b-c01625fdce7d/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>When using Docker, you may see that disk usage suddenly increases. Then, you enter the Docker container and check the capacity of the db or the files in the container, but you cannot find the cause.<br>Why is that?<br>The reason is simple.<br>This is because containers share disk volumes, and garbage data values ​​from the server accumulate on those disk volumes for a long time.<br>It is mainly accumulated in the server container that handles logic, but if left for a long time, it will also accumulate in other auxiliary containers such as databases.<br>
<br>I also had a ton of garbage accumulated in mariaDB, nginx, Grafana, phpadmin, etc.
<br>To put it simply, the cause is that the volumes of deleted or unused images or containers have piled up, creating this situation.<br>What should be done in this situation?<br>For times like this, Docker has prepared commands.<br>It is docker system prune .<br>First, let me explain the method. <br>docker ps -a 
복사<br>First, check the currently running containers with the above command and select containers with large capacity.<br>(In fact, if the server's capacity is insufficient, all containers are in trouble.)<br>Then the<br>docker stop &lt;container_id&gt;

---------------------------------

All containers are stopped

docker stop all
복사<br>Stop the container with the above command.<br>Then delete the container with the command below.<br>docker rm &lt;container_id&gt;
----------------------------------
Delete all containers

docker rm $(docker ps -a -q)
복사<br>This part will only mention the commands. (Usually it is not necessary. Run it when there is no change in capacity -&gt; But be careful to delete only unused images.)<br>Check all existing images:<br>docker images
복사<br>Delete a specific image:<br>docker rmi $(docker images -q)

복사<br>Next, it's time to delete any unused data from Docker.<br>Delete unused volumes:<br>docker volume prune
복사<br>Delete all unused containers, images, volumes, and networks:<br>docker system prune -a
복사<br>Re-creating and running containers to fulfill the above assumptions would provide a dramatic increase in capacity.<br>I got 3 terabytes.<br>Normally, you can just use the docker volume prune command to delete the above volume, but I had to deal with capacity issues again in less than 3 months when I did that the first time I tried.<br>So docker system prune -a to delete unused images, volumes, containers, networks, etc.<br>was used.<br>Of course, I'm not saying you should always use that command, because you never know what problems might arise.<br>I hope that you won't have any problems with capacity when using Docker on Ubuntu using this method. It was a meaningful event to learn again that volume management is important.]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\cs\서버-관리\eng\ubuntu-docker-capacity-management(eng).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/CS/서버 관리/Eng/Ubuntu Docker Capacity Management(Eng).md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:45:02 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f03cd953-edc3-4ae4-8b00-60576cf465e8/image.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f03cd953-edc3-4ae4-8b00-60576cf465e8/image.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[우분투 Docker 용량 관리]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f03cd953-edc3-4ae4-8b00-60576cf465e8/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>회사에서 도커 사용 중에 어려운 오류를 마주쳤다. 우분투에 할당된 4테라 용량이 부족하여 기존 서비스가 먹통이 된 것이다. 처음에는 용량을 많이 차지하는 파일이나 로그를 삭제함으로 대응하면 될 줄 알았지만, 그건 근본적인 문제가 아니었다. <br>이 문제에 수 많은 시간을 소비했기에 나와 같은 개발자들을 위해 문제 해결 방법을 공유하기로 했다. 특히 나처럼 도커 서버를 개발하고 관리하는 이들에게 도움이 되었으면 좋겠다. <br><br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/72458452-fa5d-43e7-8f4b-c01625fdce7d/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>(예시 사진)<br>도커를 사용하다보면 디스크의 사용량이 갑자기 늘어나있는 광경을 볼 수 있다. 그러면 도커 컨테이너에 들어가서 db의 용량이나 컨테이너의 파일들을 뒤져보지만, 원인을 알 수 없었다. <br> 왜일까? <br>그 이유는 간단한다.  <br>컨테이너 끼리 디스크 볼륨을 공유하고 있고 그 디스크 볼륨에 오랜 시간 서버의 쓰레기 데이터 값이 쌓이기 때문이다. <br>주로 로직을 담당하는 서버 컨테이너에 쌓이지만, 오랜 시간 방치하면 데이터 베이스 같은 다른 부속 컨테이너들에도 쌓이게 된다.<br>
<br>필자는 mariaDB, nginx, Grafana, phpadmin, 등에도 어머어마한 쓰레기 값이 쌓여있었다.
<br>원인을 간단하게 설명하자면, 삭제되거나 사용하지 않는 이미지나 컨테이너의 볼륨이 쌓여서 저런 사태를 만들어낸 것이다. <br> 이럴 때 조치는 어떻게 해야 하는가? <br>이럴 때를 대비하여 docker 에서는 명령어 들을  준비해두었다. <br>바로 docker system prune이다.<br>먼저 방법을 설명하겠다. <br>docker ps -a 
복사<br>먼저 위 명령어로 현재 실행되고 있는 컨테이너들을 확인하고 용량이 큰 컨테이너들을 고른다.<br>(사실 서버의 용량이 모자란 정도라면 모든 컨테이너가 문제가 있는 상태이다.)<br>그리고 나서 <br>docker stop &lt;container_id&gt;

---------------------------------

모든 컨테이너 정지는 

docker stop all
복사<br>위 명령어를 통해 컨테이너를 정지시킨다.<br>그 다음 아래의 명령어로 컨테이너를 삭제한다. <br>docker rm &lt;container_id&gt;
----------------------------------
모든 컨테이너 삭제는 

docker rm $(docker ps -a -q)
복사<br>그 다음에 모든 이미지나 이미지 등을 삭제하는 것은 선택 사항이기도 하다. <br>이 부분은 명령어만 언급하겠다. (보통은 안해도 괜찮다. 용량에 변화가 없을 때에 실행. -&gt; 하지만 쓰지 않는 이미지들만 지울 수 있게 조심하자.)<br>존재하는 모든 이미지 확인:<br>docker images
복사<br>특정 이미지 삭제:<br>docker rmi &lt;image_id&gt;
복사<br>모든 이미지를 삭제하려면 다음 명령어를 사용할 수 있다:<br>docker rmi $(docker images -q)

복사<br>그 다음에는 이제 docker에서 사용되지 않는 데이터들을 삭제해줄 시간이다.<br>사용하지 않는 볼륨 삭제:<br>docker volume prune
복사<br>사용하지 않는 컨테이너, 이미지, 볼륨 및 네트워크를 모두 삭제:<br>docker system prune -a
복사<br>위 가정을 마치기 컨테이너들을 다시 만들고 실행하면 획기적인 용량 확보가 가능할 것이다.<br>필자는 3테라를 확보했다.<br>보통은 위 볼륨 삭제 과정에서 docker volume prune 이 명령어만 사용하고 마쳐도 되지만, 필자는 첫 번째 시도 때 그렇게 했다고 3달도 되지 않아 또 용량 문제에 시달렸다.<br>그렇기에 쓰지 않는 이미지와 볼륨, 컨테이너, 네트워크 등을 삭제 하는 docker system prune -a<br>를 사용했다.<br>물론 무조건 저 명령어를 쓰라는 건 아니다. 무슨 문제가 생길 지도 모르기 때문이다.<br> 이 방법을 사용하여 우분투에서 도커를 사용할 때에 용량 문제에 시달리지 않길 바란다. 볼륨 관리가 중요하다는 것을 또 한번 배우게 되어 뜻 깊은 사건이었다.]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\cs\서버-관리\kor\우분투-docker-용량-관리.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/CS/서버 관리/kor/우분투 Docker 용량 관리.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:43:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f03cd953-edc3-4ae4-8b00-60576cf465e8/image.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f03cd953-edc3-4ae4-8b00-60576cf465e8/image.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Active Directory란?]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>]<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/cf0ba30b-ac69-496e-9b51-a58076dd2d7e/image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Active Directory란 컴퓨터 네트워크의 공통 구성 요소 관리를 AD(Active Directory) 라는 단일 저장소에 중앙 집중화하는 것입니다. 좀 더 쉽게 설명하자면 회사 직원들의 계정 정보(ID, Password)와 컴퓨터에 대한 정보, 그리고 강제하고자 하는 정책들(ex 비밀번호는 9자리 이상) 에 대한 정보를 저장하는 데이터 베이스 같은 거라고 생각하면 됩니다. 저는 회사 서버를 관리하는 입장이라 익숙하지만, 처음 들을 때는 다소 난해할 수 있습니다.  이 Active Directory를 실행하는 서버를 DC(도메인 컨트롤러)라고 합니다. <br>
장점
<br>중앙 집중식 ID 관리: 네트워크의 모든 사용자를 쉽게 컨트롤하고 제어할 수 있습니다.<br>
보안 정책 관리: Active Directory에서 직접 보안 정책을 구성하고 필요에 따라 네트워크를 통해 사용자와 컴퓨터에 적용할 수 있습니다.<br>마음대로 네트워크와 네트워크 내에 단말기에 정책을 강요할 수 있는 등에 편의성이 있습니다. 컴퓨터 하나하나마다 설정을 바꿔주는 건 매우 번거로우니 이런 방법은 매우 편리하죠.<br>
구성
<br>모든 Windows 도메인의 책심은 AD DS(Active Directory 도메인 서비스)입니다. 이 서비스는 네트워크에 존재하는 모든 "객체"의 정보를 보유하는 카탈로그 역할을 합니다. 객체에는 사용자, 그룹, 프린터, 공유 등등이 있습니다.<br><br>사용자는 두 가지 유형의 객체로 나타낼 수 있습니다.<br>
<br>사람: 사용자는 일반적으로 직원처럼 네트워크에 접근하는 조직 안 의 사람을 의미합니다.(회사 직원)
<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/2240c28c-4725-46d9-8986-841d0e3ff4e0/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>
<br>서비스: IIS 또는 MSSQL과 같은 서비스에 사용할 서비스를 정의할 수 있습니다. 이 경우으 ㅣ사용자는 특정 서비스를 실행하는 데 필요한 권한만 갖습니다.
<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/f500239b-d2d2-4785-91d3-b1bd96611d4e/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/8a395244-72fd-4e25-8412-99aee61a8b83/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><br>기계는 AD 도메인에 가입하는 모든 컴퓨터에 대한 것입니다. 기계는 보안 주체로 간주되며 일반 사용자와 마찬가지로 계정이 할당됩니다. 이 계정은 도메인 내에서 제한된 권한을 갖습니다.<br>컴퓨터 계정 자체는 할당된 컴퓨터의 로컬 관리자이며 일반적으로 컴퓨터 자체를 제외한 다른 사람이 접근할 수 있지만, 비밀번호가 있으면 로그인 가능합니다. <br>주의!: 컴퓨터 계정 비밀번호는 자동으로 교체되며 일반적으로는 120개의 임의의 문자로 구성됩니다.<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/09210179-107a-46f6-b6ef-0ba922829fc4/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><br>말 그대로 사용자 그룹입니다. 그룹에 사용자를 추가하여 손쉽게 관리할 수 있습니다. 해당 사용자는 그룹에 부벼되어 있는 모든 권한을 자동으로 상속받게 됩니다. 보안 그룹은 보안 주체로도 간주되므로 네트워크 리소스에 대한 권한을<br>
자길 수 있습니다.<br>주의!) 그룹은 사용자와 컴퓨터를 모두 구성원으로 가질 수 있습니다. 필요한 경우에 다른 그룹도 포함될 수 있습니다.<br>아래는 그룹의 예입니다.<br><br>
    
    
    도메인 관리자: 이 그룹의 사용자는 전체 도메인에 대한 관리 권한을 갖습니다. 기본적으로 이들은 DC를 포함하여 도메인의 모든 컴퓨터를 관리할 수 있습니다.
    
    서버 운영자: 이 그룹의 사용자는 도메인 컨트롤러를 관리할 수 있습니다. 관리 그룹 구성원 자격은 변경할 수 없습니다.
    
    백업 운영자: 이 그룹의 사용자는 권한을 무시하고 모든 파일에 액세스할 수 있습니다. 컴퓨터에서 데이터 백업을 수행하는 데 사용됩니다.
    
    계정 운영자: 이 그룹의 사용자는 도메인의 다른 계정을 만들거나 수정할 수 있습니다.
    
    도메인 사용자: 도메인의 모든 기존 사용자 계정을 포함합니다.
    
    도메인 컴퓨터: 도메인에 있는 모든 기존 컴퓨터를 포함합니다.
    
    도메인 컨트롤러: 도메인의 모든 기존 DC를 포함합니다.
    

<br><br>사용자와 시스템을 분류할 수 있는 컨테이너 개체입니다. 주로 유사한 정책 요구 사항을 가진 사용자 집합을 정의하는 데 사용됩니다. 예를 들자면 영업 부서의 직원은 개발 부서의 직원과 다른 정책 집합을 적용할 가능성이 높습니다. 그리고 사용자는 한번에 하나의 OU에만 속할 수 있다는 점을 기억하세요.<br><br>
    
    
    내장: 모든 Windows 호스트에서 사용할 수 있는 기본 그룹이 포함되어 있습니다.
    
    컴퓨터: 네트워크에 연결된 모든 컴퓨터는 기본적으로 여기에 배치됩니다. 필요한 경우 이동할 수 있습니다.
    
    도메인 컨트롤러: 네트워크의 DC를 포함하는 기본 OU입니다.
    
    사용자: 도메인 전체 컨텍스트에 적용되는 기본 사용자 및 그룹입니다.
    
    관리 서비스 계정: Windows 도메인의 서비스에서 사용되는 계정을 보유합니다.
    

<br>추가) 그룹 정책 개체(GPO)를 통해 각 OU에 대해 개별적으로 서로 다른 정책을 배포할 수 있습니다.  GPO에는 사용자 또는 컴퓨터를 대상으로 하는 정책이 포함될 수 있으므로 특정 컴퓨터 및 ID에 대한 기준을 설정할 수 있습니다.<br>
<br>보안 그룹과 조직 단위의 차이
<br>조직 단위: 정책을 적용하는데 주로 사용<br>
보안 그룹: 리소스에 대한 권한을 부여하는 데 사용<br><br>이부분은 사용자도 기계도 비슷합니다. 용도에 따라 장치와 사용자를 분리하는 것입니다. 인트라넷용 컴퓨터, 개발팀 개인 컴퓨터 등등은 서로 분리하는 것이 좋은 것 처럼 말입니다.<br><br>Windows Domian을 사용하는 경우 모든 자격 증명은 도메인 컨트롤러에 저장이 됩니다. 사용자는 이 자격 증명을 사용하여 서비스에 인증을 시도하고 서비스는 도메인 컨트롤러에 인증이 올바른지 요청하죠.<br>
인증에는 두 가지 프로토콜을 사용할 수 있습니다. 저도 해킹 공부 하면서 간간히 접한 프로토콜들입니다.<br>Kerberos : 최신 버전의 Windows에서 사용됩니다. 이는 최근 도메인의 기본 프로토콜입니다.
NetNTLM: 호환성을 위해 유지되는 레거시 인증 프로토콜입니다.

NetNTLM은 더 이상 사용하지 않는 경우가 많다고 들었지만, 대두분의 네트워크에는 두 프로토콜이 살아있습니다. <br><br>기업이 성장하면 네트워크도 커집니다. 당연한 결과죠. 서비스가 많아지고 관리할 정보들이 늘어나면 네트워크의 크기도 커지니까요.  이때 커지는 방식을 저희는 알고 있습니다. 알고리즘이든, 플로우 차트든, 반드시 보게 되는 구조니까요.<br>맞습니다. 트리 구조입니다. <br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/26ad27f9-1911-450e-be22-017ff2279379/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Active Diretory는 여러 도메인 통합을 지원하므로 네트워크를 독립적으로 관리할 수 있는 단위로 분할할 수 있습니다. 동일한 네임스페이스를 공유하게 만들어서 해당 도메인들을 tree 형태로 결합할 수 있습니다.<br>도메인이 영국 및 미국 지점에 대해 두 개의 하위 도메인으로 분할된 경우 루트 도메인 과 및라는 두 개의 하위 도메인 thm.local이 있는 트리를 구축할 수 있으며 각각에는 해당 AD , 컴퓨터 및 사용자가 있습니다..<br>이 분할된 구조를 통해 도메인에서 누가 무엇에 액세스할 수 있는지 더 효과적으로 제어할 수 있습니다. 영국의 IT 인력은 영국 리소스만 관리하는 자체 DC를 갖게 됩니다. 예를 들어 영국 사용자는 미국 사용자를 관리할 수 없습니다. 이러한 방식으로 각 지점의 도메인 관리자는 해당 DC를 완전히 제어할 수 있지만 다른 지점의 DC는 제어할 수 없습니다. 트리의 각 도메인에 대해 정책을 독립적으로 구성할 수도 있습니다.<br>하지만 다른 네임 스페이스를 가진 회사들끼리 합병되는 경우도 잦습니다. 이럴 때는 어떻게 해야할까요? 맞습니다. 나무 목이라는 한자 두개가 모여 수풀 림이라는 한자가 되듯이, 도메인도 숲이 되면됩니다. 서로 다른 네임스페이스를 가진 여러 트리를 동일한 네트워크로 통합하는 것을 포레스트라고 합니다 .<br>여러 도메인을 트리와 포레스트로 구성하면 관리 및 리소스 측면에서 훌륭하게 구획화된 네트워크를 가질 수 있습니다. 그러나 특정 시점에 THM UK 의 사용자는 MHT ASIA 서버 중 하나에 있는 공유 파일에 액세스해야 할 수도 있습니다. 이를 위해서는 트리와 포레스트에 배열된 도메인이 신뢰 관계 로 결합됩니다 .<br>간단히 말해서, 도메인 간에 신뢰 관계가 있으면 다른 도메인의 사용자에게 다른 도메인의 리소스에 액세스할 수 있는  권한을 부여할 수 있습니다. 이 관계는 단방향으로도, 양방향으로도 구성할 수 있습니다. <br>이렇게 Active Directory에 알아봤습니다. 평소에 서버를 관라할 때에는 개념만 알고 넘어갔는데 다시 제대로 지식을 되새김해보니 더 넓게 시야가 트이네요. 앞으로 좀 더 많이 보안, 네트워크 지식을 알아가야 겠습니다.]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\cs\서버-관리\kor\active-directory란.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/CS/서버 관리/kor/Active Directory란.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 01:47:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/cf0ba30b-ac69-496e-9b51-a58076dd2d7e/image.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/cf0ba30b-ac69-496e-9b51-a58076dd2d7e/image.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Security has two major domains:<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/65a8a861-3aaf-442a-991f-232116da09d9/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>"Offensive"<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/56d20474-5660-4d9b-8bba-a47f0262b89f/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>"Defensive"<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/75a04b29-89f7-479d-87d5-634526bbab9f/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>In this article, I will introduce the basic areas of security.<br>
Offensive Security
<br>Offensive security involves the process of finding vulnerabilities in applications to infiltrate computer systems, exploit software bugs, and gain unauthorized access to applications.<br>In short, it means acting like a “hacker” to stop hackers.<br>This concept is similar to the image we have of hackers.<br>
Defensive Security
<br>Defensive security differs somewhat from offensive security because it involves two main tasks.<br><br>
    
        
        
        
            Intrusion prevention and response tasks encompass a variety of defensive security activities. The primary tasks include:
            
                <br>User Cybersecurity Awareness
                <br>Asset Documentation and Management
                <br>System Updates and Patching
                <br>Preventive Security Device Configuration
                <br>Logging and Monitoring Device Setup
            
        
        
            
            The Blue Team is central to defensive security. The primary tasks of the Blue Team include:
            
                <br>Establishing policies in advance and educating employees
                <br>Preparing defenses against attacks on the system
            
            In essence, the Blue Team primarily handles defensive security. It involves establishing policies in advance, educating employees, and preparing the system to defend against attacks.
        <br>
    

<br><br>
    
    This document explains two key topics related to defensive security: SOC handling threat intelligence and DFIR (Digital Forensics and Incident Response).
    
        
        The SOC plays a central role in maintaining the security of an organization, detecting, analyzing, and responding to threats. The SOC uses security devices and technologies to monitor the network in real-time, identify potential threats, and address them quickly.
        
            <br>Threat Intelligence: The SOC uses Threat Intelligence to gather and analyze information on new threats and vulnerabilities. This intelligence is crucial for improving security policies and preparing defenses against threats.
            <br>Real-Time Monitoring: The SOC team monitors networks, systems, and applications in real-time to detect suspicious activities and investigate them promptly.
            <br>Incident Response: The SOC recognizes incidents quickly and minimizes threats through appropriate response procedures.
        
    
    
        
        DFIR combines Digital Forensics and Incident Response, focusing on investigating and responding to security incidents within an organization. Malware analysis plays a crucial role in this process.
        
            <br>Digital Forensics: Digital Forensics within DFIR involves collecting and analyzing evidence after a security incident to determine the cause and impact of the attack.
            <br>Incident Response: Incident response involves the quick handling and recovery process following a security incident. The goal is to minimize damage and take preventive measures to avoid similar incidents in the future.
            <br>Malware Analysis: Malware analysis is a significant part of DFIR, focusing on understanding the behavior and structure of malicious software to identify the attacker’s intent and strategy. This helps in formulating response strategies and strengthening security systems.
        
    <br><br><br>
    
        
        
            <br>Preparation: A prepared and trained team is essential to handle incidents. Ideally, various measures should be taken to prevent incidents from occurring in the first place.
            <br>Detection and Analysis: The team should have the necessary resources to detect incidents and further analyze the detected events to assess their severity.
            <br>Containment, Eradication, and Recovery: Once an incident is detected, it is crucial to stop it from spreading to other systems, eradicate the threat, and ensure the affected systems are restored. For example, if a system is infected with a virus, containment would involve preventing the virus from spreading to other systems, eradication would involve treating the virus, and recovery would ensure proper system restoration.
            <br>Post-Incident Activity: After a successful recovery, a report is generated, and lessons learned are shared to prevent similar incidents in the future.
        
    
  
    
        
        Malware refers to malicious software, including programs, documents, and files that can be stored on a disk or transmitted over a network. There are various types of malware, and the main types include the following:
        
            <br>Virus: A virus is a piece of code (a part of a program) that attaches itself to a program. It is designed to spread from one computer to another and can modify, overwrite, and delete files on the infected computer. The results can range from slowing down the computer to rendering it unusable.
            <br>Trojan Horse: A Trojan horse is a program that appears to perform a desirable function but actually performs malicious activities. It can create a backdoor in the system, allowing unauthorized access.
            <br>Worm: Unlike viruses, worms do not require a host program and can spread autonomously. They often exploit vulnerabilities in operating systems or applications to replicate and spread across networks.
            <br>Ransomware: Ransomware is a type of malware that encrypts the victim’s files and demands a ransom for the decryption key. It can cause significant damage to organizations and individuals.
        
    



]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\tryhackme\jr-penetration-tester\보안-소개\eng\1..html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/보안 소개/Eng/1..md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:59:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/65a8a861-3aaf-442a-991f-232116da09d9/image.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/65a8a861-3aaf-442a-991f-232116da09d9/image.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/06b48fdf-5dff-492a-80b8-2a1b4d6921ea/image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>"공격적"<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/4d88ac01-36ea-4dab-a268-85541ef4075b/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>"방어적"<br><img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/accfc629-2578-4a58-bb39-cfe21457a9a7/image.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>이 글에서는 기본적인 보안 영역에 대한 소개를 진행해보려고 합니다.<br>
공격적인 보안
<br>
<br>
공격적인 보안은 컴퓨터 시스템에 칩입하고 소프트웨어 버그를 악용하고, 응용 프로그램에 대한 무단 액세스를 얻기 위해 응용 프로그램의 허점을 찾는 과정입니다.

<br>
요컨대 해커를 막기 위해 “해커” 처럼 행동하는 것을 의미합니다.

<br>저희가 생각하는 해커의 이미지랑 비슷하다고 할 수 있겠네요<br>

<br>방어적인 보안

<br>
<br>방어적 보안은 두 가지 주요 작업과 관련되어 있기 때문에 공격적 보안과 다소 차이가 있습니다.
<br><br>
    
        
        
        
            
            침입 방지 및 대응 작업에는 다양한 방어 보안 작업이 포함됩니다. 주요 작업은 다음과 같습니다:
            
                <br>사용자 사이버 보안 인식
                <br>자산 문서화 및 관리
                <br>시스템 업데이트 및 패치
                <br>예방적 보안 장치 설정
                <br>로깅 및 모니터링 장치 설정
            
        
        
        
            
            
                침입이 발생했을 때, 이를 신속하게 감지하고 대응하는 것이 중요합니다. 이를 위해 다음과 같은 조치를 취해야 합니다:
            
            
                <br>실시간 모니터링 시스템 설정
                <br>의심스러운 활동에 대한 알림 설정
                <br>즉각적인 사고 대응 계획 마련
                <br>사고 후 분석 및 보고서 작성
            
        
        
        
            
            블루팀은 방어적 보안의 핵심입니다. 블루팀의 주요 작업은 다음과 같습니다:
            
                <br>미리 정책을 수립하고 직원들을 교육
                <br>시스템에 대한 공격에 대비하여 방어 체계를 준비
                <br>사고 발생 시 신속하게 대응하고 복구 절차를 이행
            
            즉, 블루팀은 주로 공격에 대비하는 방어적 보안 작업을 담당합니다.
        <br>
            
            이 문서에서는 방어적 보안과 관련된 두 가지 주요 주제인 위협 인텔리전스를 다루는 SOC와 DFIR(Digital Forensics and Incident Response)에 대해 설명합니다.
        <br>
            
            SOC는 조직의 보안을 유지하고 위협을 탐지, 분석, 대응하는 중심적인 역할을 합니다. SOC는 보안 장비와 기술을 사용하여 실시간으로 네트워크를 모니터링하고, 잠재적인 위협을 식별하며, 이를 신속하게 처리합니다.
            
                <br>위협 인텔리전스: SOC는 위협 인텔리전스(Threat Intelligence)를 사용하여 새로운 위협과 취약점에 대한 정보를 수집하고 분석합니다. 이러한 인텔리전스는 보안 정책을 개선하고 위협에 대한 대비책을 수립하는 데 중요한 역할을 합니다.
                <br>실시간 모니터링: SOC 팀은 네트워크, 시스템, 애플리케이션을 실시간으로 모니터링하여 의심스러운 활동을 탐지하고 이를 신속히 조사합니다.
                <br>사고 대응: SOC는 사고 발생 시 이를 신속하게 인식하고, 적절한 대응 절차를 통해 위협을 최소화합니다.
            
        <br>
            
            DFIR은 디지털 포렌식과 사고 대응을 결합한 용어로, 조직에서 발생한 보안 사고를 조사하고 대응하는 데 초점을 맞추고 있습니다. 이 과정에서 맬웨어 분석이 중요한 역할을 합니다.
            
                <br>디지털 포렌식: DFIR의 디지털 포렌식은 보안 사고가 발생한 후 증거를 수집하고 분석하여 공격의 원인과 영향을 파악합니다.
                <br>사고 대응: 사고 대응은 보안 사고가 발생했을 때, 이를 신속하게 처리하고 복구하는 과정을 포함합니다. 이는 손실을 최소화하고, 유사한 사고가 재발하지 않도록 예방 조치를 취하는 것을 목표로 합니다.
                <br>맬웨어 분석: 맬웨어 분석은 DFIR의 중요한 부분으로, 악성 소프트웨어의 행동과 구조를 분석하여 공격자의 의도와 전략을 파악합니다. 이를 통해 대응 방안을 수립하고 보안 체계를 강화할 수 있습니다.
            
        <br>
            
            
                <br>준비: 사고를 처리할 준비가 되어 있고 교육을 받은 팀이 필요합니다. 이상적으로는 처음부터 사고가 발생하지 않도록 다양한 조치를 취해야 합니다.
                <br>탐지 및 분석: 팀은 사고를 탐지하는 데 필요한 리소스를 보유하고 있으며, 감지된 사건을 추가로 분석하여 심각도를 파악하는 것이 중요합니다.
                <br>봉쇄, 근절 및 복구: 사고가 감지되면 다른 시스템에 영향을 미치지 않도록 중지하고 제거하며 영향을 받은 시스템을 복구하는 것이 중요합니다. 예를 들어, 시스템이 컴퓨터 바이러스에 감염된 것을 알게 되면 바이러스가 다른 시스템으로 확산되는 것을 막고(억제), 바이러스를 치료(박멸)하며 시스템 복구를 보장합니다.
                <br>사고 후 활동: 성공적인 복구 후에는 보고서를 생성하고 학습된 교훈을 공유하여 향후 유사한 사고를 방지합니다.
            
        <br>
            
            맬웨어는 악성 소프트웨어를 의미하며, 이는 디스크에 저장되거나 네트워크를 통해 전송될 수 있는 프로그램, 문서 및 파일을 포함합니다. 맬웨어에는 다양한 유형이 있으며, 주요 유형은 다음과 같습니다.
            
                <br>바이러스: 바이러스는 자신을 프로그램에 첨부하는 코드 조각(프로그램의 일부)입니다. 한 컴퓨터에서 다른 컴퓨터로 확산되도록 설계되었으며, 감염된 컴퓨터에서 파일을 변경, 덮어쓰기 및 삭제할 수 있습니다. 그 결과 컴퓨터의 성능 저하부터 심각한 경우 사용할 수 없게 되는 상황이 발생할 수 있습니다.
                <br>트로이 목마: 트로이 목마는 겉으로는 유용해 보이는 기능을 제공하지만, 그 아래에 악성 기능을 숨기는 프로그램입니다. 예를 들어, 피해자는 수상한 웹사이트에서 비디오 플레이어를 다운로드하여, 공격자가 시스템을 완전히 제어할 수 있도록 허용할 수 있습니다.
                <br>랜섬웨어: 랜섬웨어는 사용자의 파일을 암호화하는 악성 프로그램입니다. 암호화된 파일은 특정 암호를 입력하지 않으면 읽을 수 없게 되며, 공격자는 사용자가 '몸값'을 지불하면 암호를 제공하여 파일을 복구할 수 있도록 합니다.
            
        <br>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    

]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\tryhackme\jr-penetration-tester\보안-소개\kor\1..html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/보안 소개/Kor/1..md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:59:08 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/06b48fdf-5dff-492a-80b8-2a1b4d6921ea/image.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://velog.velcdn.com/images/tkops365/post/06b48fdf-5dff-492a-80b8-2a1b4d6921ea/image.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240812103222.png" src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812103222.png"><br>Here is the English translation of your text with the specified formatting:<br>"A penetration test is an authorized audit of the security and defenses of a computer system, which the system owner has agreed to. In this sense, it has the legitimacy of penetration, but it must not exceed the agreed-upon scope.<br>Exceeding this scope would turn the test into hacking.<br><br>
    
        
        
        <br>    &lt;h2&gt;Rules of Engagement (ROE)&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ROE is a document created at the early stages of a penetration testing contract.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Section&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Authorization&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This section of the document provides explicit authorization for the engagement to be conducted. This authorization is essential for legally protecting individuals and organizations during the activities performed.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Scope&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This section of the document defines the specific target that the engagement should cover. For example, the penetration test may apply only to a specific server or application, not the entire network.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Rules&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;The rules section precisely defines the techniques allowed during the engagement. For example, it may specify that techniques like phishing attacks are prohibited, but MITM (Man-in-the-Middle) attacks are allowed.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Penetration Testing Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Penetration testing can have various objectives and goals within its scope. Therefore, penetration tests are not all the same, and there is no one-size-fits-all approach to how penetration testers should proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;The steps performed by a penetration tester during an engagement are referred to as the &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;methodology&lt;/span&gt;. A practical methodology involves actions taken in a smart way that are relevant to the current situation. Each situation may require a different methodology. For example, the methodology used to test the security of a web application may not be practical when testing the security of a network, as these are different domains.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Common Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Step&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Information Gathering&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;In this step, as much information as possible is collected about the target/organization from publicly accessible sources (e.g., OSINT and research).&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Note: This does not include system scanning.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Enumeration/Scanning&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This step involves discovering applications and services running on the system. For example, finding a web server that may be potentially vulnerable. Example: Finding a port with a vulnerable service running.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Exploitation&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This step involves exploiting the vulnerabilities found in the system or application. This may involve using publicly available exploits or exploiting application logic. Think of it as the stage where direct attacks are carried out.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Privilege Escalation&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;After successfully exploiting a system or application, this step attempts to elevate the privileges on the system. Privilege escalation can be horizontal or vertical. It can involve gaining higher privileges from the initial account or permissions, such as gaining administrator access.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Post-Exploitation&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This step includes several sub-steps:&lt;br&gt;
                1. Finding other hosts that could be targets.&lt;br&gt;
                2. What additional information can be gathered from the host now that higher privileges have been obtained?&lt;br&gt;
                3. Deleting traces of the intrusion.&lt;br&gt;
                4. Reporting.
            &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Types&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OSSTMM&lt;/strong&gt;: The OSSTMM provides a detailed framework for testing strategies for systems, software, applications, communications, and the human aspect of cybersecurity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This methodology mainly focuses on how these systems and applications communicate, so it includes methodologies for:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Communications (telephone, VoIP, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Wired networks&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Wireless communications&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
복사<br>
]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\tryhackme\jr-penetration-tester\침투-테스트\eng\1..html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/침투 테스트/Eng/1..md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 01:32:41 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812103222.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812103222.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Security Principles]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240812105418.png" src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812105418.png"><br><br>
    
        
        
        
        Principles of information security to protect data and safeguard systems from abuse.
        
        
        The model of confidentiality, integrity, and availability (CIA) consists of these three principles and has become an industry standard today. This model helps in making decisions about the value of the data and what is needed in a business.
        
        <br>    &lt;h4&gt;Confidentiality&lt;/h4&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="important"&gt;Confidentiality&lt;/span&gt; is about protecting data from unauthorized access and misuse. Organizations always store some form of sensitive data within their systems. Providing confidentiality is about protecting this data from unintended access by anyone other than the authorized individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h4&gt;Integrity&lt;/h4&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="important"&gt;Integrity&lt;/span&gt; ensures that data remains unaltered except for authorized changes. Data can be changed due to careless handling, system errors, or unauthorized access. In security principles, integrity is maintained if information remains unchanged during storage, transmission, and usage, ensuring unauthorized individuals cannot alter the data (e.g., data breaches).&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h4&gt;Availability&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be useful, data must always be accessible and available to users. &lt;span class="important"&gt;Availability&lt;/span&gt; is an essential element.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;3. Principle of Least Privilege&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is important to manage and correctly define various levels of access to information technology systems that individuals need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The level of access granted to individuals is determined by two basic factors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;The role/function&lt;/span&gt; of the individual within the organization&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;The sensitivity of the information&lt;/span&gt; stored in the system&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two key concepts used in assigning and managing user access rights are &lt;span class="important"&gt;PIM (Privileged Identity Management)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="important"&gt;PAM (Privileged Access Management)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially, these two concepts may seem similar. However, they are different. PIM is used to translate user roles within an organization into access roles within the system. In contrast, PAM primarily deals with managing the privileges associated with system access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A critical aspect of access and privilege control is the &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;principle of least privilege&lt;/span&gt;. In simple terms, users should be given only the minimum privileges necessary to perform their duties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PAM integrates more than just access assignment. It also includes security policy enforcement such as password management, policy auditing, and reducing the attack surface of systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;4. Security Models&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before discussing security models in detail, let's consider the three elements of CIA: confidentiality, integrity, and availability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to security models, any system or technology that stores information is referred to as an &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;information system&lt;/span&gt;, and this is how systems and devices are referenced in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's look at some popular and effective security models used to achieve the three elements of CIA.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Bell-La Padula Model&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="important"&gt;Bell-La Padula Model&lt;/span&gt; is used to achieve confidentiality. This model assumes a hierarchical structure within an organization where everyone's responsibilities/roles are well defined.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This model operates by granting access to data (referred to as objects) based on a &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;"write-up, read-down"&lt;/span&gt; rule. It ensures that individuals can access only the data they need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Advantages&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;The model’s policies can be applied to actual organizational hierarchies and vice versa.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Full confidentiality is not achieved as users may learn about the existence of objects they cannot access.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Implementation and understanding are straightforward and proven successful.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;The model relies heavily on trust within the organization.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Biba Model&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="important"&gt;Biba Model&lt;/span&gt; is similar to the Bell-La Padula Model but focuses on integrity rather than confidentiality in CIA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This model applies rules summarized as &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;"write-up, read-down."&lt;/span&gt; This means that a subject can write to information at its own level or lower but can only read data at its level or higher.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Advantages&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;The model is straightforward to implement.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;With multiple levels of access and objects, security levels can easily be overlooked when applying security controls.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;It addresses both confidentiality and data integrity, overcoming some limitations of the Bell-La Padula Model.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;It often causes delays in business operations. For example, in a hospital where this model is applied, a doctor might not be able to read notes written by a nurse, leading to delays.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Biba Model is used in situations or organizations where integrity is more critical than confidentiality. For example, in software development, developers may need access only to the code necessary for their tasks and not to other critical information.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;5. Threat Modeling and Incident Response&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="important"&gt;Threat modeling&lt;/span&gt; is the process of reviewing, improving, and testing security protocols in an organization's IT infrastructure and services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An important step in the threat modeling process is identifying potential threats and vulnerabilities that a system or application may face.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The threat modeling process is similar to risk assessments performed in the workplace for employees and customers, following similar principles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Preparation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Identification&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Mitigation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Review&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To assist, frameworks such as &lt;span class="important"&gt;STRIDE&lt;/span&gt; (Spoofing, Tampering, Repudiation, Information Disclosure, Denial of Service, and Elevation of Privilege) and &lt;span class="important"&gt;PASTA&lt;/span&gt; (Process for Attack Simulation and Threat Analysis) are available. Below, we will discuss STRIDE in detail. STRIDE, developed by two Microsoft security researchers in 1999, remains influential today. STRIDE includes six key principles.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Principle&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Spoofing&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This principle involves authenticating requests and users accessing the system. Spoofing includes malicious parties pretending to be someone else. Measures such as access keys (e.g., API keys) or encryption through signatures help address this threat.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Tampering&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This principle involves providing tamper-evident measures to ensure data integrity. Data accessed should be maintained in its original, accurate state, similar to how groceries are sealed to preserve them.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Repudiation&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This principle directs the use of logging for system or application activities to track services.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Information Disclosure&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Applications or services handling information from multiple users should be properly configured to only display information relevant to the owner.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Denial of Service&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Applications and services use system resources, so measures should be taken to prevent the abuse of applications/services from causing the entire system to go down.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Elevation of Privilege&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;This is the worst-case scenario for applications or services, where a user can escalate their privileges to a higher level, such as an administrator. This often leads to further exploitation or information disclosure and is a significant concern in security incidents.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;Security breaches are referred to as &lt;span class="important"&gt;incidents&lt;/span&gt;. Despite stringent threat models and secure system designs, incidents do occur. The actions taken to address and remediate threats are known as &lt;span class="important"&gt;Incident Response (IR)&lt;/span&gt; and are a crucial part of a career in cybersecurity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident response processes are often covered in security certifications such as those offered by CISA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incidents are classified using urgency and impact ratings. Urgency is determined by the type of attack faced, the location of the affected system, and the impact on business operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incidents are responded to by &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Computer Security Incident Response Teams (CSIRTs)&lt;/span&gt; that are pre-organized with technical knowledge of the current incident. To successfully resolve an incident, the following six steps of incident response are often listed in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Action&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Preparation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Are resources and plans in place to handle security incidents?&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Identification&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Have threats and threat actors been correctly identified so that we can respond?&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Containment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Can the threat/security incident be contained to prevent impact on other systems or users?&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Eradication&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Eliminate the active threat.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Recovery&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Perform a thorough review of the affected systems to restore normal operations and business.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&lt;span class="highlight"&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;What can be learned from the incident? For instance, if it was caused by a phishing email, better training for employees to detect phishing emails should be provided.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
복사<br>
]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\tryhackme\jr-penetration-tester\침투-테스트\eng\security-principles.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/침투 테스트/Eng/Security Principles.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 04:23:09 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812105418.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812105418.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240812103300.png" src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812103300.png"><br>침투&nbsp;테스트는&nbsp;시스템&nbsp;소유자가&nbsp;동의한&nbsp;컴퓨터&nbsp;시스템의&nbsp;보안&nbsp;및&nbsp;방어에&nbsp;대한&nbsp;승인된&nbsp;감사\니다이러한&nbsp;의미에서&nbsp;침투의&nbsp;합법성을 가지고 있지만, 그외 부분을 벗어나면 안됩니다!<br> 그 외의 부분을 벗어나면 테스트가 아니라 해킹이 되기 때문입니다. <br><br>
    
        
        
        <br>    &lt;h2&gt;교전 규칙 (ROE)&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ROE는 침투 테스트 계약의 초기 단계에서 생성되는 문서입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;부분&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;설명&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;허가&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;문서의 이 영역은 수행할 계약에 대한 명시적 허가를 제공합니다. 이 권한은 수행하는 활동에 대해 개인과 조직을 법적으로 보호하는 데 필수적입니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;테스트 범위&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;문서의 이 영역은 계약이 적용되어야 하는 특정 대상의 범위를 정하는 것입니다.  예를 들어 침투 테스트는 전체 네트워크가 아닌 특정 서버나 애플리케이션에만 적용될 수 있습니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;규칙&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;규칙은 참여 중에 허용되는 기술을 정확하게 정의합니다. 예를 들어 규칙에 피싱 공격과 같은 기술은 금지되지만 MITM(Man-in-the-Middle) 공격은 허용된다고 구체적으로 명시할 수 있습니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;침투 테스트 방법론&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;침투 테스트는 범위 내에서 다양한 목적과 목표를 가질 수 있습니다. 이 때문에 침투 테스트는 동일하지 않으며 침투 테스터가 어떻게 접근해야 하는지에 대해 절대적인 기준은 존재하지 않습니다. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;참여 중에 침투 테스터가 수행하는 단계를 &lt;span class="highlight"&gt;방법론&lt;/span&gt;이라고 합니다. 실제로 유용한 방법론은 효율적인 방법으로 취해진 조치가 현 상황에 잘 들어맞습니다.  각 상황마다 들이맞는 방법론이 다른 것입니다. 예를 들어, 웹 애플리케이션의 보안을 테스트하는 데 사용할 방법론을 갖는 것은 네트워크의 보안을 테스트해야 할 때 실용적이지 않습니다. 두 영역은 다르기 때문입니다.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;공통적인 단계&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;단계&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;설명&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;정보 수집&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 단계에서는 대상/조직에 대해 공개적으로 액세스할 수 있는 정보(예: OSINT 및 연구)를 최대한 많이 수집합니다.&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;참고: 여기에는 시스템 스캔이 포함되지 않습니다.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;열거/스캐닝&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 단계에는 시스템에서 실행 중인 응용 프로그램 및 서비스 검색이 포함됩니다. 예를 들어 잠재적으로 취약할 수 있는 웹 서버를 찾는 것입니다. ex) 취약한 서비스 돌고 있는 포트 찾기&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;착취&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 단계에는 시스템 또는 애플리케이션에서 발견된 취약성을 활용하는 작업이 포함됩니다. 이 단계에서는 공개 익스플로잇을 사용하거나 애플리케이션 로직을 익스플로잇할 수 있습니다. 직접적으로 공격하는 단계라고 생각하면 쉽습니다. &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;권한 에스컬레이션&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;시스템 또는 애플리케이션을 성공적으로 악용한 후 이 단계는 시스템에 대한 권한을 더 높은 수준으로 올리려는 시도입니다. 수평적 및 수직적으로 에스컬레이션할 수 있습니다.  처음 접속했던 계정이나 권한에서 관리자와 같은 높은 권한을 얻는 것 등이라고 보면 됩디ㅏ. &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;착취 후&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 단계에는 몇 가지 하위 단계가 포함됩니다.&lt;br&gt;
                1. 대상이 될 수 있는 다른 호스트찾기&lt;br&gt;
                2. 높은 권한을 취득하였기 때문에 호스트에서 어떤 추가 정보를 수집할 수 있습니까?&lt;br&gt;
                3. 침입 기록 삭제&lt;br&gt;
                4. 보고
            &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;종류&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OSSTMM&lt;/strong&gt;: OSSTMM은 시스템, 소프트웨어, 애플리케이션, 통신 및 사이버 보안의 인적 측면에 대한 테스트 전략의 상세한 프레임워크를 제공합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;이 방법론은 주로 이러한 시스템과 애플리케이션이 통신하는 방식에 초점을 맞추므로 다음을 위한 방법론이 포함됩니다:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;통신(전화, VoIP 등)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;유선 네트워크&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;무선 통신&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
복사<br>
]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\tryhackme\jr-penetration-tester\침투-테스트\kor\1..html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/침투 테스트/Kor/1..md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 01:33:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812103300.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812103300.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[2. 보안 원칙]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240812105418.png" src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812105418.png"><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="A_A-s-Tech-Blog/Obsidian_Remote/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/보안 소개/Kor/1." data-href="A_A-s-Tech-Blog/Obsidian_Remote/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/보안 소개/Kor/1." href="A_A-s-Tech-Blog\Obsidian_Remote\정보보안\tryhackme\Jr Penetration Tester\보안 소개\Kor\1." class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">1.</a><br>
    
        
        
        
        데이터를 보호하고 남용으로부터 시스템을 보호하는 정보 보안의 원칙
        
        
        기밀성, 무결성 및 가용성(CIA),  세 가지로 구성된 이 모델은 오늘날 빠르게 업계 표준이 되었습니다. 이 모델은 적용되는 데이터의 가치와 비즈니스에서 필요한 결정을 내리는데 도움이 됩니다.
        
        <br>    &lt;h4&gt;기밀성&lt;/h4&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;기밀성은 무단 액세스 및 오용으로부터 데이터를 보호하는 것입니다. 조직은 항상 어떤 형태의 민감한 데이터를 시스템에 저장합니다. 기밀성을 제공하는 것은 의도하지 않은 누군가로부터 이 데이터를 보호하는 것과 같습니다. 즉 허용된 누군가 이외에 데이터에 접근하는 것을 막아야 합니다. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h4&gt;무결성&lt;/h4&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;무결성은 보안의 삼 요소 중에서 승인된 변경이 없는 한 데이터가 언제나 무결한상태를 유지하는 것입니다. 부주의한 접근 및 이용, 정보 시스템의 오류, 무단 접근 및 이용 등으로 인해 정보가 변경될 수 있습니다.  보안 원칙에서는 정보를 수정하지 않고 저장되거나, 전송 및 사용하는 동안 정보가 변경되지 않은 상태로 유지될 때 무결성이 충족되는 것으로 판단합니다. 이를 위해서는 권한이 없는 사람이 데이터를 변경할 수 없도록 조치를 취해야 합니다(예: 기밀 위반).&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h4&gt;가용성&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;데이터가 유용하려면 언제든 사용자가 데이터를 사용할 수 있고 액세스할 수 있어야 합니다. 가용성은 그러한 요소입니다. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;3. 특권의 원칙&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;개인이 필요로 하는 정보 기술 시스템에 대한 다양한 액세스 수준을 관리하고 올바르게 정의하는 것이 중요합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;개인에게 제공되는 액세스 수준은 두 가지 기본 요소에 따라 결정됩니다:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;조직 내 개인의 역할/기능&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;시스템에 저장되는 정보의 민감도&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;개인의 액세스 권한을 할당하고 관리하는 데 두 가지 주요 개념이 사용되며, PIM(Privileged Identity Management) 및 PAM(Privileged Access Management)이 사용됩니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;처음에는 이 두 개념이 같은 것처럼 보일 수 있습니다. 그러나 그 둘은 서로 다릅니다. PIM은 조직 내의 사용자 역할을 시스템의 액세스 역할로 변환하는 데 사용됩니다. 반면 PAM은 무엇보다도 시스템의 액세스가 갖는 권한 관리입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;권한 및 액세스 제어를 논의할 때 필수적인 것은 최소 권한의 원칙입니다. 간단히 말해, 사용자에게는 최소한의 권한만 부여되어야 하며, 의무를 수행하는 데 절대적으로 필요한 권한만 부여되어야 합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PAM은 액세스 할당 이상의 기능을 통합합니다. 또한 비밀번호 관리, 정책 감사, 시스템이 직면하는 공격 표면 감소와 같은 보안 정책 시행을 포함합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;4. 보안 모델&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;보안 모델에 대해 자세히 논의하기 전에 CIA의 세 가지 요소인 기밀성, 무결성 및 가용성을 생각해 봅시다. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;보안 모델에 따르면 정보를 저장하는 모든 시스템 또는 기술을 정보 시스템이라고 하며, 이 작업에서 시스템 및 장치를 참조하는 방법입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CIA 3요소의 세 가지 요소를 달성하는 데 사용되는 인기 있고 효과적인 몇 가지 보안 모델을 살펴보겠습니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Bell-La Padula 모델&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bell-La Padula 모델은 기밀성을 달성하는 데 사용됩니다. 이 모델에는 모든 사람의 책임/역할이 잘 정의되어 있는 조직의 계층 구조와 같은 몇 가지 가정이 있습니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;이 모델은 엄격하게 알 필요가 있는 데이터(객체라고 함)에 대한 액세스 권한을 부여하여 작동합니다. 이 모델은 "쓰기 금지, 읽기 금지" 규칙을 사용합니다. 필요한 사람이 필요한 데이터에 접근 가능한 모델입니다. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;장점&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;단점&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 모델의 정책은 실제 조직 계층에 적용될 수 있으며 그 반대도 가능합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;사용자가 개체에 액세스할 수 없더라도 개체의 존재에 대해 알게 되므로 완전한 기밀이 아닙니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;구현 및 이해가 간단하고 성공적인 것으로 입증되었습니다.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 모델은 조직 내의 많은 신뢰에 의존합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    
    &lt;h3&gt;Biba 모델&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biba 모델은 틀림없이 Bell-La Padula 모델과 동일하지만 CIA의 무결성을 위한 것입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;이 모델은  데이터 및 사용자에게 "기록하지 않고 읽지 않음"으로 요약할 수 있는 규칙을 적용합니다. 이 규칙은 주체가 해당 권한 수준 이하의 정보에 내용을 작성하거나 쓸 수 있지만 해당 수준 위의 데이터만 읽을 수 있음을 의미합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;장점&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;단점&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 모델은 구현이 간단합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;여러 수준의 액세스 및 개체가 있습니다. 보안 제어를 적용할 때 보안 수준을 쉽게 간과할 수 있습니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;기밀성과 데이터 무결성을 모두 해결하여 Bell-La Padula 모델의 한계를 해결합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;종종 비즈니스 내에서 지연이 발생합니다. 예를 들어 의사는 이 모델이 적용된 병원에서 간호사가 작성한 메모를 읽을 수 없습니다. 그래서 종종 지연이 발생합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biba 모델은 기밀성보다 무결성이 더 중요한 조직이나 상황에서 사용됩니다. 예를 들어 소프트웨어 개발에서 개발자는 작업에 필요한 코드에만 액세스할 수 있습니다. 데이터베이스 등과 같은 중요한 정보에 액세스할 필요가 없을 수도 있습니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;h2&gt;5. 위협 모델링 및 사고 대응&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;위협 모델링은 조직의 정보 기술 인프라 및 서비스에 있는 보안 프로토콜을 검토, 개선 및 테스트하는 프로세스입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;위협 모델링 프로세스의 중요한 단계는 애플리케이션 또는 시스템이 직면할 수 있는 가능성 있는 위협, 시스템 또는 애플리케이션이 취약할 수 있는 취약성을 식별하는 것입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;위협 모델링 프로세스는 직원과 고객을 위해 작업장에서 수행되는 위험 평가와 매우 비슷합니다. 원칙과 같습니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;준비&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;식별&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;완화&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;검토&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;이를 돕기 위해 STRIDE(스푸핑, 데이터 변조, 부인 위협, 정보 공개, 서비스 거부 및 권한 상승) 및 PASTA(공격 시뮬레이션 및 프로세스를 위한 프로세스)와 같은 프레임워크가 있습니다. 아래에서 STRIDE에 대해 자세히 설명하겠습니다. 1999년 두 명의 Microsoft 보안 연구원이 작성한 STRIDE는 오늘날에도 큰 영향을 끼치고 있습니다. STRIDE에는 6가지 주요 원칙이 포함되어 있습니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;원칙&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;설명&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;스푸핑&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 원칙에서는 시스템에 액세스하는 요청 및 사용자를 인증해야 합니다. 스푸핑에는 자신을 다른 사람으로 잘못 식별하는 악의적인 당사자가 포함됩니다. 액세스 키(예: API 키) 또는 암호화를 통한 서명은 이 위협을 해결하는 데 도움이 됩니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;탬퍼링&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;시스템 또는 애플리케이션에 변조 방지 조치를 제공함으로써 데이터에 무결성을 제공하는 데 도움이 됩니다. 액세스하는 데이터는 완전하고 정확하게 유지되어야 합니다. 식료품점에서 식품을 보존하기 위해 밀봉하는 것과 같은 원래입니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;부인&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이 원칙은 추적할 시스템 또는 응용 프로그램에 대한 활동 로깅과 같은 서비스 사용을 지시합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;정보 공개&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;여러 사용자의 정보를 처리하는 애플리케이션 또는 서비스는 소유자와 관련된 정보만 표시되도록 적절하게 구성해야 합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;서비스 거부&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;애플리케이션과 서비스는 시스템 리소스를 사용하므로 애플리케이션/서비스의 남용으로 인해 전체 시스템이 다운되지 않도록 조치를 취해야 합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;권한 승격&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;이것은 애플리케이션이나 서비스에 대한 최악의 시나리오입니다. 이는 사용자가 더 높은 수준, 즉 관리자의 권한으로 권한을 에스컬레이션할 수 있음을 의미합니다. 이 시나리오는 종종 추가 악용 또는 정보 공개로 이어집니다. 이는 보안 사고에서 많은 비중을 차지하곤 합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;보안 위반을 인시던트(사고)라고 합니다. 모든 엄격한 위협 모델과 안전한 시스템 설계에도 불구하고 사고는 발생합니다. 위협을 해결하고 수정하기 위해 취한 조치를 사고 대응(IR)이라고 하며 사이버 보안의 전체 경력 경로입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 이에 대한 사고 대응 프로세스등은 CISA와 같은 보안 자격증에서 자주 출제되곤 합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;인시던트는 긴급도 및 영향 등급을 사용하여 분류됩니다. 긴급성은 직면한 공격의 유형, 영향을 받는 시스템에 의해 영향이 결정되는 위치 및 비즈니스 운영에 미치는 영향에 따라 결정됩니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;사고는 시스템 및/또는 현재 사고에 대한 기술적 지식을 갖춘 직원 그룹으로 미리 구성된 컴퓨터 보안 사고 대응 팀(CSIRT)에 의해 대응됩니다. 인시던트를 성공적으로 해결하기 위해 이러한 단계는 종종 아래 표에 나열된 인시던트 대응의 6단계라고 합니다.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;행동&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;설명&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;준비&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;보안 사고를 처리하기 위한 자원과 계획이 마련되어 있습니까?&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;신분증&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;우리가 대응할 수 있도록 위협과 위협 행위자가 올바르게 식별되었습니까?&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;방지&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;다른 시스템이나 사용자가 영향을 받지 않도록 위협/보안 사고를 억제할 수 있습니까?&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;근절&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;활성 위협을 제거합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;회복&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;영향을 받는 시스템에 대한 전체 검토를 수행하여 정상적인 운영으로 비즈니스를 되돌립니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;교훈&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;사건에서 무엇을 알 수 있습니까? 즉, 피싱 이메일로 인한 것이라면 피싱 이메일을 감지하도록 직원을 더 잘 교육해야 합니다.&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
복사<br>
]]></description><link>a-a-tech-blog\정보보안\tryhackme\jr-penetration-tester\침투-테스트\kor\2.-보안-원칙.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a-a-tech-blog/정보보안/tryhackme/Jr Penetration Tester/침투 테스트/Kor/2. 보안 원칙.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 04:58:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812105418.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\pasted-image-20240812105418.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>